the atoms like each other the different
degrees oxygen for instance in the air
would like to be next to carbon and if
they get a near each other they snap
together if they're not too close though
they repel and they go apart so they
don't know that they could snap too yet
it's just as if you had a ball it was
trying to climb a hill then there was a
hole I could go into like a volcano hole
a deep one it's rolling along it doesn't
go down in the deep hole because if it
starts to climb the hill and then rolls
away again but if your men made it go
fast enough it'll fall into the hole and
so if it sets something like wood in
oxygen there's carbon in the wood from a
tree and the oxygen comes and hits it
common but not hard enough it just goes
away again the air is always fun
nothing's happening if you can get it
faster by heating it up somehow
somewhere somehow get it started a few
of them come fast they go over the top
so to speak they come close enough of
the carbon and snap in and that gives a
lot of jiggly motion which might hit
some other atoms making those go faster
so they can climb up and bump against
other carbon atoms and they jiggle and
they make Mother's jiggle and you get a
terrible catastrophe which is one after
the other all these things are going
faster and faster and snapping in and
the whole thing is changing that
catastrophe is a fire that it's just a
way of looking at it and these things
are happening they perpetual once it
gets started it keeps on going the heat
makes the other atoms capable of
reaching to make more heat to make other
atoms and so on so this terrible
snapping is producing a lot of jiggling
and if I put with all that activity of
the atoms there and I put a cup of
coffee over that massive wood that's
doing this it's going to get a lot of
jiggling so that's what the heat of the
fire is and then of course say if you
see this is what happens we just start
to figure just go out and I wonder where
how did it get started why is it that
the woods been sitting around all this
time with the oxygen all this time and
it didn't do this earlier or something
where did I get this front
while it came from a tree and the
substance of the tree is carbon where
did that come from that comes from the
air it's carbon dioxide from the air
people look at trees and they think it
comes out of the ground the plants crawl
out of the ground but if you ask where
the substance comes you find out where
do they come from the trees come out of
the air they surely come out of there no
they come out of the air if the carbon
dioxide in the air goes into the tree
and it changes it kicking out the oxygen
and pushing the oxygen away from the
carbon and leaving the carbon substance
with water water comes out of the ground
you see only to have to get in there
came out of the air didn't did it came
down from the sky
so in fact most of a tree almost all of
the trees out of the ground outside it's
out of the air there's a little bit from
the ground some minerals and so forth
now of course I told you the oxygen and
we know the oxygen and carbon stick
together bet very tight how is it the
tree is so smart is to manage take the
carbon dioxide which is the carbon
oxygen nicely combined and undo that so
easy ah life life has some mysterious
force no the sun is shining and it's the
sunlight that comes down and knocks
these oxygen away from the carbon so it
takes sunlight to get the plant to work
and so the Sun all the time is doing the
work of separating the oxygen away from
the cob and the oxygen is some kind of
terrible by-product which it spits back
into the air and leaving the carbon and
water and stuff to make the substance of
the tree then when we take the substance
of the tree its to get the fireplace and
the is the Holy oxygen made by these
trees and all the carbon would would
much prefer to be close together again
and once you let the heat to get it
started it continues and makes an awful
lot of activity while it's going back
together again and all this nice light
and everything comes out and everything
is being undone you're going back from
carbon and oxygen back to carbon dioxide
and the light and heat that's coming out
that's the light and heat of the Sun
that went in
so it's sort of stored Sun that's coming
out when you burn it a log next question
how is it the Sun is so jiggly so hot I
got to stop somewhere I'll leave you
something to imagine